<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://robertpuccinelli.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://robertpuccinelli.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-12T22:38:34+00:00</updated><id>https://robertpuccinelli.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Robert Puccinelli</title><subtitle>Learn a bit more about Robert Puccinelli, his research and personal projects.</subtitle><author><name>Robert R Puccinelli</name><email>robert@robertpuccinelli.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Toastmasters: (0) Ice Breaker</title><link href="https://robertpuccinelli.com/toastmasters/2020/02/08/ice-breaker.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Toastmasters: (0) Ice Breaker" /><published>2020-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://robertpuccinelli.com/toastmasters/2020/02/08/ice-breaker</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://robertpuccinelli.com/toastmasters/2020/02/08/ice-breaker.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One’s first speech at Toastmasters is a ~5 minute ice breaker that is used to introduce yourself to the club. The speech presented here describes what happens to my mind when it is struck with social anxiety and how it impacts my interaction with others. The speech is formatted to indicate short and long pauses, which I decided to apply after reading a few chapters of “Speak Like Churchill, Stand Like Lincoln”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;speech&quot;&gt;Speech&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Fellow Toastmasters..

We're all here because we understand that communication is important.
We understand that we have room for improvement..
Obviously,
I am no exception..

During the first 3 years of my life,
I could barely hear..
Chronic ear infections made it difficult for me to speak
because the world sounded like it was underwater.
I mumbled my way through the next several years,
and only my family knew how to translate what I was saying..
My ability to speak would continue to challenge me for more than two decades..

I would like to believe that we have all had bad interviews at one point..

My first one was when I was 14.
I was asked to describe a project that I had spent months preparing for and executing.
My mind was frozen.
No thoughts existed.
I could not utter any words.

My second was in front of a panel of naval officers when I was 17.
My third was when I being recruited as an air force officer when I was 21.
My fourth was yesterday..
I could not describe a basic concept of a project I had spent 3 years working on..
It's humiliating..

My body shakes uncontrollably
when I have to speak about myself in front of people I don't know.
Insecurity progresses to social anxiety,
and each word spoken belies an intense mental storm.
My mind struggles to maintain clarity as it fights the darkness..

As they say,
you are your own worst enemy..

I am here today because I am filled with rage
and I need to overcome this silent oppression.
I am envious of those who can speak so eloquently,
and at the same time deeply disappointed in myself..
I, too, know those words..
I, too, have some great ideas..
I, too, have done impactful work..

However,
the world doesn't care about you if you cannot communicate.

I do not expect Toastmasters to cure this debilitation,
but I do hope that it will help me forge the tools I need
to climb my own personal Everest.
I look forward to learning from your speeches and feedback
and I appreciate the opportunity to improve myself.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;metrics&quot;&gt;Metrics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Required time: 4-6 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Average practice time: 3:40&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Presented time: 3:14&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ah counts: 1 Er&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Best Speech” vote: Under time / not qualified&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;feedback&quot;&gt;Feedback&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;speech-evaluator&quot;&gt;Speech Evaluator&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Authenticity appreciated&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Speech ended abruptly when audience was looking forward to hearing more&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work on adding more content&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never leave the lectern empty without handing it off to the next speaker&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Talk to the evaluator ahead of time so they know what to focus on evaluating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;written-notes&quot;&gt;Written Notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Dear Robert, I was deeply touched by your speech. Thanks for sharing your stories with us. Public speech and communication are difficult, but we’re all here to help you and progress ourselves.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Robert -Everyone related to your speech. -Great job taking your time in the beginning. -I noticed you have a consistent rhythm w/ pauses. Maybe vary it a little.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Robert Thank you for sharing your story with us!! I really appreciate your courage to go on the stage and tell us such a touching story. I used to shy away from speaking in public due to my language barrier. Although mine might still be very different from your situation. After joining TM for 3 years, I do feel the small community helped me a lot in terms of communication and expressing myself. Hope it’ll help you too! Again, great job on your ice breaker. -Y”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“really touching speech and I think you are doing great given the short preparation time! Connection to a &lt;strong&gt;deeper level&lt;/strong&gt;. Definitely looking forward to your next speech.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Great job taking the courage to do the ice breaker speech! You said your body would shake uncontrollably but I didn’t notice that until you pointed it out. You hold your posture and you spoke in a calm note, so you are already making a great start! for improvement, I would suggest you expand the story you laid out at the beginning. Those were emotional and inspiring stories and I would like to learn more.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;-vivid description of your own challenge. -although a little nervous, you spoke at a very nice tone, pace, and very organized -practice more, you will be more confident -your language is great, good writing would ensure your good speech -your body movement and gesture and eye contact are very natural -you’re good at impromptu speaking!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reflection&quot;&gt;Reflection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Too much swaying when speaking. Stand firm when movement is not needed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minor slip up on recalling correct words when giving speech&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Writing a word or two on a notepad to indicate topic of next paragraph helped immensely as I was panicking when speaking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t run away after speaking - follow proper hand off protocol&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recordings&quot;&gt;Recordings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speech:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://img.youtube.com/vi/video_id/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ice Breaker&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evaluation:&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert R Puccinelli</name><email>robert@robertpuccinelli.com</email></author><category term="toastmasters" /><category term="speech" /><summary type="html">First formal speech.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">SCI-Arc 3D Printer Recommendations and Services</title><link href="https://robertpuccinelli.com/services/2019/09/03/3d-printer-recommendations.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SCI-Arc 3D Printer Recommendations and Services" /><published>2019-09-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://robertpuccinelli.com/services/2019/09/03/3d-printer-recommendations</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://robertpuccinelli.com/services/2019/09/03/3d-printer-recommendations.html">&lt;p class=&quot;notice--info&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PURPOSE:&lt;/strong&gt; It can be a bit daunting to get started with 3D printing when there are so many options out there. On the other hand, if you have already spent some time printing, it could be fun to see what upgrades are out there to improve your printing experience. The following page is Huan Liang’s (2nd year M.Arch 1 student) and my recommendation for getting started with with 3D printing at SCI-Arc. We also discuss some upgrades that we have been testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;sidebar__right&quot;&gt;
&lt;nav class=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;&lt;h4 class=&quot;nav__title&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-reorder&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Table of Contents&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;toc__menu&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#example-prints&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-example-prints&quot;&gt;Example Prints&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#introduction&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#huans-printer-kit&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-huans-printer-kit&quot;&gt;Huan’s Printer Kit&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#kit-items&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-kit-items&quot;&gt;Kit Items&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#rationale&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-rationale&quot;&gt;Rationale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#helping-you-get-started&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-helping-you-get-started&quot;&gt;Helping you get started&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#upgrades&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-upgrades&quot;&gt;Upgrades&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#services&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-services&quot;&gt;Services&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#getting-started&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-getting-started&quot;&gt;Getting Started&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#printer-upgrades&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-printer-upgrades&quot;&gt;Printer Upgrades&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;example-prints&quot;&gt;Example Prints&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature__wrapper&quot;&gt;

  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_PrintPhotoshoot1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;3D Printed Model, ~150mmx150mm&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_PrintPhotoshoot1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_PrintPhotoshoot2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;3D Printed Model, View 2&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_PrintPhotoshoot2.jpg&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_PrintPhotoshoot3_withSupports.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Fan Duct with Supports&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_PrintPhotoshoot3_withSupports.jpg&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone at SCI-Arc has a Prusa. They are easy to use and they usually don’t have bad prints. That being said, I bet Huan that we could get prints that are just as good as a Prusa with a printer that costs significantly less. After living with the printer for a year we are both incredibly happy with our decision and want to share our experience to help you understand that &lt;strong&gt;there are other quality printers out there&lt;/strong&gt;. I am personally making this recommendation even after working with more expensive 3D printers on a daily basis (including Ultimakers, FormLabs, and Stratasys systems). Huan and I are both satisfied with the &lt;strong&gt;Ender 3 Pro&lt;/strong&gt; as an entry level printer and wouldn’t hesitate to get it again if we had a choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-center text-center width-75&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_StockEnder3Pro.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The Ender 3 Pro

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: The following Amazon Affiliate links are for items that we actually purchased or used. That being said, we want you to know that Amazon might pay us if you click on our Amazon links.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;huans-printer-kit&quot;&gt;Huan’s Printer Kit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kit-items&quot;&gt;Kit Items&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a list of what we bought for the printer - we’ll explain each item down below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Item&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Model&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Vendor&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Price ($)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3D Printer&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ender 3 Pro&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sainsmart&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2MUdhLk&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;260&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Build Plate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tempered Glass Plate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sainsmart&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2LhKezg&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Glue Sticks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.2g Clear Glue, 3 Pack&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Uhu&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2MUl1wR&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Angled Pliers&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3517&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tekton&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2ZLlO5w&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7.25&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nozzle Cleaning Kit&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.4mm Needles&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wobion&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2zOpIzV&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brass Brushes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Retractable Bristles&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ATB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2ZHiSXq&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OUR TOTAL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;~310&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rationale&quot;&gt;Rationale&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, so we bought an &lt;strong&gt;Ender 3 Pro&lt;/strong&gt;. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really liked that this printer used aluminum extrusions because they gave it more structural strength. This is important for clean prints that have smooth sides. We decided to go with the Pro version rather than the standard because there is a wider rail for the Y-axis, which provides additional stability for the build plate. Furthermore, we bought the Sainsmart version because it included extra nozzles, snips and a silicone sock for the heater to prevent our parts from getting soft during printing, which is a nice touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a known issue with the Ender 3 printers is that some of them have a bowl-shaped build plate when they leave the factory. This was so bad that we could not get reliable prints without using a raft. After contacting Sainsmart about the issue, we ended up using their &lt;strong&gt;glass build plate&lt;/strong&gt;. Glass is great because the build plate will have superior flatness and it shouldn’t wear down like plastic or magnetic plates. The Ender 3 glass also comes with a special surface coating to help remove parts when the plate cools. This is nice, but our builds were coming off a bit too easily, so we used &lt;strong&gt;Uhu glue sticks&lt;/strong&gt; to help the part stick to the plate a bit better. This is what we’ve been using ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-center text-center width-75&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_UnevenBed.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Build plate was warped when received from the factory. Solved with glass.

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ender 3 Pro came with a pair of snips to trim support, but it can be difficult to remove support that is deeper in the part. To remove those supports, we purchased &lt;strong&gt;angled pliers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is generally a good practice to keep the nozzle clean so that plastic doesn’t stick to it and drag around your print, we purchased a set of brass brushes. Also, we wanted to try some special filaments like wood. These filaments can be tricky because they can clog a nozzle. Rather than risk tossing out a good but clogged nozzle, we purchased a &lt;strong&gt;nozzle cleaning kit&lt;/strong&gt;. 0.4mm piano wire is usually good enough to do the job. We haven’t had a clog yet, so this was probably not necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the printer was set up and we learned what settings and plastics work well with our printer, Huan and I ended up with some really clean and smooth prints! The key to good prints are to have a good frame, use good plastics and use appropriate slicer settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;helping-you-get-started&quot;&gt;Helping you get started&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot of small details that are good to be aware of and keep track of as you 3D print. Things like improper build plate leveling, building your printer with gaps in the wrong place, or using the wrong slicer settings that can really throw off a print. I have worked with many printers for several years now and I can offer advice or assistance if you want help getting started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Services that may be of interest to you include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assembling your printer&lt;/strong&gt; for you to ensure that you are working off a good printer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teaching a 3D printing bootcamp class&lt;/strong&gt;:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cover different types of printers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Walk you through how to generate G-code and what settings work well for the Ender 3&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Teach how to correctly level a bed and setup a print&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Teach how to fix problems you might run into when printing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Discuss different types of filaments and how to find the right profile for your material&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Discuss simple upgrades that you can make to your system now&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upgrading your firmware and tuning the system&lt;/strong&gt; to give you safety features such as thermal runaway protection and allow you to add upgrades on your own. Tuning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install silent mainboard&lt;/strong&gt; to quiet down the motors and upgrade the firmware.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, visit the &lt;a href=&quot;#services&quot;&gt;Services&lt;/a&gt; section down below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;upgrades&quot;&gt;Upgrades&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve been using the printer for some time, we decided that it was time to make our lives easier by changing the firmware and adding some real upgrades. Our Ender 3 Pro is currently rocking the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;BLTouch for auto bed leveling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;OctoPrint server for an easy to use printer dashboard&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;8 megapixel camera for checking on prints remotely and creating timelapses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Touchscreen to access OctoPrint directly from the printer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;BLTouch&lt;/strong&gt; has been amazing because it means that we no longer need to spend minutes fiddling with the printer before starting a job or worrying that the bed might have shifted since we last used it. The auto bed leveler will map the build plate before we print and compensate for any variations in height. Perfect first layers every time. &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2ZITiRP&quot;&gt;Amazon kit&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2NUJn9o&quot;&gt;Amazon adapter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OctoPrint&lt;/strong&gt; is pretty convenient because we now have a way to expose way more functionality of the printer from the comfort of our computer. Want to see how the print is doing? Log on. Want to upload a new file? Drag and drop. Want a timelapse? Check the box. What layer am I on and how close am I to finishing? Change the tab. 1 of my 10 parts is starting to fail during the print? Cancel that object mid print and build the other 9. &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2MWgmKP&quot;&gt;Amazon Pi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2LgKcHY&quot;&gt;Amazon SD card&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Webcam&lt;/strong&gt; is a relatively cheap upgrade to the server that really lets you be away from the printer while controlling your system. &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2ZLvWey&quot;&gt;Amazon camera&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2ZLq44P&quot;&gt;Amazon cable&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Touchscreen&lt;/strong&gt; exposes some of the OctoPrint functionality without really needing to be on the computer and it gives a cleaner looking physical interface to the printer. I’m planning to upgrade the software on this unit to make it far better than the stock display. Currently using a custom designed case. &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2NO6iTP&quot;&gt;Amazon screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature__wrapper&quot;&gt;

  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_AutobedLevel.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;BLTouch Auto Bed Leveling&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_AutobedLevel.jpg&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_PrintServer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;OctoPrint Server&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_PrintServer.jpg&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_TouchscreenDisplay.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Touchscreen Display&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_TouchscreenDisplay.jpg&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_Camera.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;8MP Camera&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_Camera.jpg&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_UpgradedPrinter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Upgraded Printer&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190903_UpgradedPrinter.jpg&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;services&quot;&gt;Services&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in a service, please send an email to the address underneath my picture on the side or to robert (at) puccilabs.com . My phone number is also listed on the flier posted around SCI-Arc. If you’re interested in an upgrade that isn’t listed here, please reach out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-started&quot;&gt;Getting Started&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Assemble printer - $75&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3D Printing Bootcamp - $30&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Upgrade firmware and tune system - $30&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install silent mainboard (upgrades firmware) - $65&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;printer-upgrades&quot;&gt;Printer Upgrades&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt; FIRMWARE UPGRADE REQUIRED &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Auto bed leveling upgrade - $100&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;OctoPrint server upgrade - $125
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Camera upgrade - $50&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Access server anywhere upgrade - $50&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Touchscreen upgrade - $80&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Robert R Puccinelli</name><email>robert@robertpuccinelli.com</email></author><category term="services" /><category term="build" /><category term="printing" /><summary type="html">A set of 3D printer recommendations and upgrades for quality prints.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Resources for Embedded Development</title><link href="https://robertpuccinelli.com/tools/2019/05/21/embedded-resources.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Resources for Embedded Development" /><published>2019-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://robertpuccinelli.com/tools/2019/05/21/embedded-resources</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://robertpuccinelli.com/tools/2019/05/21/embedded-resources.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Briefly, I found the following resources to be useful for embedded hardware development. More resources will be added over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;microcontrollers&quot;&gt;Microcontrollers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jaycarlson.net/microcontrollers/&quot;&gt;The Amazing $1 Microcontroller&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; A very informative and thorough review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;debugging&quot;&gt;Debugging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://interrupt.memfault.com/blog/gdb-for-firmware-1&quot;&gt;Debugging Firmware with GDB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; A nice, short walkthrough for remote debugging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://darkdust.net/files/GDB%20Cheat%20Sheet.pdf&quot;&gt;GDB Cheatsheet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Tidy collection of GDB commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.techbeamers.com/how-to-use-gdb-top-debugging-tips/&quot;&gt;GDB Tutorial for C&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Compiler optimizations for debugging and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;firmware&quot;&gt;Firmware&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collabora.com/news-and-blog/blog/2019/02/18/modern-usb-gadget-on-linux-and-how-to-integrate-it-with-systemd-(part-1)/&quot;&gt;Modern USB Gadgets on Linux, Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Make and integrate USB gadgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collabora.com/news-and-blog/blog/2019/03/27/modern-usb-gadget-on-linux-and-how-to-integrate-it-with-systemd-part-2/&quot;&gt;Modern USB Gadgets on Linux, Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Make and integrate USB gadgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collabora.com/news-and-blog/blog/2019/05/23/testing-video4linux2-drivers-like-a-boss/&quot;&gt;Testing V4L2 Drivers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert R Puccinelli</name><email>robert@robertpuccinelli.com</email></author><category term="tools" /><category term="hardware" /><category term="electronics" /><summary type="html">A useful list of resources for hardware development.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Build Your Own: Automotive Head Unit</title><link href="https://robertpuccinelli.com/build/2019/01/21/updating-jeep-head-unit.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Build Your Own: Automotive Head Unit" /><published>2019-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://robertpuccinelli.com/build/2019/01/21/updating-jeep-head-unit</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://robertpuccinelli.com/build/2019/01/21/updating-jeep-head-unit.html">&lt;p class=&quot;notice--info&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PURPOSE:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Provide a DIY alternative to expensive commercial head units. The following in-depth guide is designed to allow anyone to rebuild their system in the event of a break-in or upgrade their system at their own discretion. I would like to thank my insurance company, AAA, for supporting this rebuild by allowing me to cash settle to repair/replace my system after it was damaged by theft. Overall benefits of this system include:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;A.&lt;/strong&gt; breaking the system down into individual modules that are less expensive to replace in the event of theft,&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;B.&lt;/strong&gt; modernizing technologically outdated systems,&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;C.&lt;/strong&gt; allowing virtually unparalleled customizability of an infotainment system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The automotive head unit is the interface for the infotainment system of a vehicle and is often a prime target for theft due to retained aftermarket value. In older vehicles, it was primarily the stereo. In newer vehicles, it has transformed into a multi-functional touch screen interface for audio, navigation, vehicle diagnostics, rearview cameras, and even portals for an Android or Apple phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Security features have been implemented in some units that make them not worth stealing such as detachable face plates (stereo rendered inoperable and therefore unsellable) or complex integration with a vehicle (rendering the system useless in a different vehicle). These features, in addition to other technologies such as universal phone pairing, have supposedly resulted in a decline of stereo theft. Obviously, as I can comment firsthand, theft still exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are in the market for a new head unit, there are plenty of nice (or budget) commercial systems available and there are also DIY options available which can give you a high degree of customizability at a competitive price. If a DIY system interests you, I would recommend that you familiarize yourself with what options are available. What I have written here is a single build and, given that technology is always advancing, it could be obsolete by tomorrow. That being said, this will still be decades better than some stock units. The following guide is written with sufficient detail that anyone with a TJ Wrangler will be able to follow the guide and end with identical results. Owners of different vehicles may require a few modifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we’re building here is a system with many of the conveniences of modern vehicles in a technologically challenged vehicle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Touch screen interface (Nexus 7, 2013)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Built-in navigation (Nexus 7, 2013)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Android Auto + Apple CarPlay integration (hardware dongle)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stereo integration (Digital-to-analog converter)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;FM radio (Software defined radio tuner app + hardware receiver)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Backup camera (Software app + camera hardware)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;OBDII Interface (Software app + OBDII module)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Microphone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Protective cover (Shield the unit from the elements when the top is down and possibly hide the system from potential thieves?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who are fortunate enough to still have their stereos, I hear that beautiful mornings can lead to an ugly evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190121_Sunrise.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190121_Sunrise.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190121_StolenStereo.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190121_StolenStereo.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;center&gt;Morning and evening of November 26.&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;parts-list-and-files&quot;&gt;Parts List and Files&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section encompasses everything that is required to build the system to give you an overview of what is involved. After listing the components, each section will examine why certain components were chosen in greater detail. Although software files are listed below, they are largely for my own reference of what was used in the event that I have to rebuild the system. &lt;strong&gt;I strongly encourage others to download files from the original provider&lt;/strong&gt; and not from this page. There may be more recent versions available and you can’t be certain that these files haven’t been tampered with. The links to the original provider are listed. Hardware is listed first because the software is largely dependent on the employed hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hardware-description-and-rationale&quot;&gt;Hardware Description and Rationale&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;align-center width-75 text-center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/190121_VehicleInfotainment.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Graphical depiction of implemented infotainment system.

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll work our way from left to right in the figure above. The star of the show is the Nexus 7, 2013 edition. It is not the most advanced tablet in the market, but the screen has virtually a perfect form factor that matches a double DIN head unit and it has some of the most extensive kernel options available. We’ll be running Timur’s Kernel v4.0 to integrate the tablet into the Jeep as permanent hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To assert the tablet as the host of the system, all connections must be routed through the on-the-go (OTG) adapter. From here, a special Y cable connects to the powered USB hub to provide the tablet with a high amp supply and to route data. This USB hub is powered by a 12V line that is only active when the ignition is on. This allows the tablet and peripherals to enter a deep sleep / off state when there is no auxiliary power - saving your vehicle’s battery when off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, the peripherals are completely user dependent and there is quite a bit of flexibility in options. Not everyone will be interested in having Android Auto / Apple CarPlay, OBDII diagnostics, or a microphone in their vehicle. I did this mainly because I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The OBDII unit sits in your vehicle’s OBDII port and can transmit data directly to the Nexus 7 via bluetooth. The OBDII port is still powered when the vehicle is off, so a minor modification will be made to the bluetooth unit to only power it when auxiliary power is available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The radio receiver connects to the USB hub and is controlled by an app on the tablet. It is quite capable of receiving all FM channels and more; however, it is unable to receive AM broadcasts. The transmission frequency for most AM stations is too low for this unit to detect, but other units (such as a HAM upconverter) should make AM accessible if desired. This receiver employed here connects to a F to SMA adapter, which will allow you to plug the antenna into the unit. I was unable to find a Motorola to SMA adapter, so we’ll have to modify the adapter a bit to make things work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few video cards are usable with Android 6.0.1, but I went for what I thought was the simplest. A subset of USB video cards (UVC) should not require any drivers on any system (including Windows 2000). A lot of cheap cards say they are UVC but still require drivers, which defeats the purpose. Try to avoid those ones to make your life easier. The video card is connected to the USB hub and also has its power switched by an automotive 12V relay. Whenever the reverse gear is engaged, the reverse wire is brought to 12V. When this happens, the relay will power the UVC, which will then begin transmitting video data directly to the Nexus 7. Furthermore, the backup camera also taps the 12V line that power the reverse lights, so the camera will be powered simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The microphone isn’t anything special. In this case, it’s just a USB mic with an integrated driver. A microphone that plugs into the 3.5mm jack on the tablet might work as well. Alternatively, there are bluetooth microphones that might be a better choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The phone dongle is a bit of an experiment. This unit should allow for Android Auto or Apple CarPlay to be retrofitted onto older head units, but no one has done it with a Nexus 7 as far as I’m aware of. This dongle should allow the phone to be directly controlled by tablet. I previously installed QuickCharge 3 USB ports in my Jeep for rapid charging of mobile devices. I currently plan to connect the data pins from one of the ports directly to the phone dongle so that the phone can charge quickly while also supporting connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least is the digital to analog converter (DAC). This takes digital audio signals from the Nexus 7 and converts them into an analog signal that is sent to the vehicle’s speakers. Some DACs have been problematic in builds with microphones for unclear reasons. I think some DACs have a microphone input port that change the DAC from being an output device to being an input/output device. The 6.0.1 Android OS might only support one input at a time, so the standalone microphone input might be disabled as long as the I/O DAC is connected. To connect the DAC to the speakers, RCA lines will be installed for the left and right audio channels. The Nexus 7 only has left and right outputs - an amplifier or some other system will be required for additional channels like front and back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hardware-components&quot;&gt;Hardware Components&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;notice--primary&quot;&gt;The Amazon Affiliate links below help fund future Build Your Own projects at no cost to you. If you do not wish to support this work, the model number is provided for your reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Item&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Model&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Provider&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Cost&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Early TJ Double Din Bezel&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Metra 95-6549 70-1817&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ebay.com/itm/JEEP-WRANGLER-TJ-1997-2002-DOUBLE-DIN-DASH-BEZEL-RADIO-STEREO-MOUNTING-KIT/192628453170?ssPageName=STRK%3AMEBIDX%3AIT&amp;amp;_trksid=p2060353.m2749.l2649&quot;&gt;eBay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$79.98&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tablet&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nexus 7, 2013&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2G2NSuI&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$75.02&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Powered USB Hub&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Kootion H6C22&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2Wmdto8&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$19.99&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Phone Link Dongle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Carlinkit HW01-01&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2TfegW7&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$60.99&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USB DAC&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Signstek Mini USB DAC&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2MB0ryw&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$21.99&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Radio Receiver&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;NooElec NESDR Smart&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2Ue3wYa&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$23.95&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USB Video Capture Card&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;EasyCAP FBA_UVC Black&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2G2RmgM&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$9.94&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Backup Camera&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;DohonesBest 4350450562&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2FRWk0N&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$18.99&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USB Microphone&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;MAONA AU-410&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2sNV5XK&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$14.99&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;OBDII Reader&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Panlong PL-B02&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2RWmqGs&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$10.98&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USB OTG Adapter&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Cablecc B01KCBSKSA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2MEhmAA&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$6.30&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;USB Y Cable&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;SaiTech B00VV24L7E&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2Wnr26I&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$4.99&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;SMA Coaxial Adapter&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;DHT AD012&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2TingcT&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$5.50&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Antiglare Screen Protector&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;BoxWave bw-862-4841-0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2sLInZD&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$9.95&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;RCA Plugs, 1.5ft&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monoprice 105346&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2Sb7Utx&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$6.64&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total cost of all hardware for a 2001 TJ installation at the time of the build: &lt;strong&gt;$370.20&lt;/strong&gt;. (Note: I already had a Nexus 7. The $300 cost and reuse of old tech helped motivate this project.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you already have a vehicle with a double din bezel and aren’t interested in having Android Auto or Apple CarPlay features, you could reduce the cost to $229.23. If you don’t have 12V automotive relays or a method of connecting loose ends of wires, those components will incur a small additional cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;software-modules&quot;&gt;Software modules&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although there is a high degree of flexibility in hardware, it is greatly outmatched by that of the software. I’ll list a few applications that I believe are essential for my use case and will leave all other remaining preferences to the reader. None of the following modules are required to implement an Android head unit and it may be worth your time to explore other options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automotive Kernel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
First and foremost, I chose to build the head unit off of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/timurskernel/comments/51lhgf/v40_for_android_601/&quot;&gt;Android 6.0.1 with Timur’s v4.0 kernel&lt;/a&gt;. This setup allows the Nexus 7 to charge while also acting as the OTG host for the USB peripherals. It also includes some nice features for an automotive setting such as automatic deep sleep when the ignition is off or automatically launching a backup camera when the reverse gear is engaged. Timur provides instructions on how to install everything, but I will go into a bit more detail in the build guide below because some things were not readily apparent to me. Potential problems and workarounds with this method are listed in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/timurskernel/comments/5elxa7/pitfalls_and_solutions/&quot;&gt;Pitfalls and Solutions&lt;/a&gt; thread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blackout Screen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It may be a bit silly to list this function as a second priority, but it is somewhat important to me. Before my previous head unit was stolen, there were many times when I did not need it powered or preferred to keep the cab dark. The tablet is currently set to never sleep when the ignition is on, primarily because the power button is not accessible behind the bezel. Since it never sleeps, the interior is always illuminated. I implemented a gesture control to launch the &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=net.jomyut.blackscreen&quot;&gt;BlackScreen&lt;/a&gt; app when a specific spot on my tablet is double tapped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clean Interface&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It’s important to me that I have a clean home screen with no bloatware. If I’m driving, I don’t accidentally want to tap the (in my opinion) useless Google Search bar. I also want to maximize the real estate of the screen, so no dock. As you might observe from this website, I prefer minimalistic designs. I found that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=is.shortcut&quot;&gt;Evie Launcher&lt;/a&gt; was perfect for my use case and would highly recommend it. I was able to clear the home screen completely and only have a large clock and essential app shortcuts. Most of the settings in the launcher were disabled by choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vehicle Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I’m not completely settled on the dashboard yet, but I’m currently evaluating &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=is.shortcut&quot;&gt;AutoMate&lt;/a&gt;. It’s nice because it has separate features on different pages, but transitioning between pages often takes me multiple attempts. Alternatives include &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.nezdroid.cardashdroid&quot;&gt;Car dashdroid&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.autolauncher.motorcar.free&quot;&gt;Car Launcher&lt;/a&gt;. The benefits of a system like this is that it can cleanly organize navigation, phone call, media operations, and OBDII readouts. I’ll have a stronger opinion when I get to installing the tablet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Modules&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Radio Tuner: &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=marto.androsdr2&quot;&gt;SDR Touch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
OBDII Readout: &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.prowl.torquefree&quot;&gt;Torque Lite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Gesture Control and Remove Navigation Bar: &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.xda.nobar&quot;&gt;Navigation Gestures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Pop Up Navigation Bar: &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.navigation.bar.customize.soft.keys&quot;&gt;Custom Navigation Bar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Backup Camera : VCam2 (Shipped with Timur’s Kernel) &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.xda-developers.com/devdb/project/dl/?id=26261&quot;&gt;Alternative&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Media Controls on Navigation Bar: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/timurskernel/comments/4hdc56/mediavolume_buttons_for_navbar_marshmallow/&quot;&gt;cliffeed mod&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Phone Dongle App: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carlinkit.com/autokit.apk&quot;&gt;Carlinkit Autokit.apk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following files are listed in the event that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/timurskernel/comments/51lhgf/v40_for_android_601/&quot;&gt;files from Timur’s Reddit thread&lt;/a&gt; are lost. I would advise you to not download these if the official versions are still available:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://app.box.com/s/pnc461hr9023na6qx3ln1kad31b8owdc&quot;&gt;TWRP 3.0.2-0 Debian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://app.box.com/s/mfwx5jfm83q8pzv1yvft344p6kc76yp0&quot;&gt;Timur Kernel N7 2013 v4.0 Final Flo Debian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://app.box.com/s/72vhwf94bd7n8jhxp262v6nuom1tlxvy&quot;&gt;SuperSU v2.76&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Also required is the factory MOB30X Android image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;build-guide&quot;&gt;Build Guide&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The build guide is quite extensive - we’ll cover the software aspect first before the hardware. The primary software guide can be found on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/timurskernel/comments/51lhgf/v40_for_android_601/&quot;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt;, the following is largely a reprint of what is there in addition to a few other details. Timur’s original commentary is &lt;em&gt;italicized&lt;/em&gt; and additional commentary I included is written in normal font. The TJ natively supports a 1.5 DIN (who does that?) and may require some trimming of the dash to place the Nexus 7. Since the Nexus is so thin, it might not be required but be prepared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;installation-of-android-tools&quot;&gt;Installation of Android Tools&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before your system can push software from your computer to the Nexus, some development tools have to be installed on your computer. ADB allows debugging of Android over USB and fastboot allows you to unlock the bootloader and push custom software onto the unit. Either Google search how to install those tools or run the following on OSX:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;brew cask install android-platform-tools&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timur’s instructions:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Now enable the “USB debugging” feature on your Android device. In order to do so, open Settings and then open “Developer options”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you cannot find “Developer options” in the list, go to “About tablet” and click the “Build number” five times in a row, until you see a toast message, telling you that: You are now a Developer. Now leave “About tablet” and you should be able to see and open “Developer options”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Under “Developer options” you should now be able to enable “USB debugging”. While you are in “Developer options”, you may also want to enable “Stay awake”. This feature is useful, if you want to use the FI-mode feature.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With your tablet connected to the PC, you should now be able to open a command shell on your PC and run the following commands. This is for testing connectivity only:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;adb shell date&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This should display the current time and date of your Android device on your PC. If this doesn’t work, try the following:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;adb devices&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This should show the “List of attached Android devices” in the command shell on your PC. If this does not show at least one Android device (with a serial number and a name), you should try unplugging and reconnecting the USB cable. You may need to confirm ADB connectivity in a dialog box on your Android device. If you are not able to establish ADB-over-USB connectivity, google for “adb windows” and/or “adb windows usb drivers”. And possibly install/update the required USB drivers. Continue only, if the adb tool is working properly.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unlocking-the-bootloader&quot;&gt;Unlocking the Bootloader&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timur’s instructions:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;If your tablet’s bootloader is not yet unlocked, you need to unlock it now. This can be done in two quick steps by running the following commands in the command shell on your PC:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;adb reboot bootloader&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And then, when the tablet shows the bootloader screen, run:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;fastboot oem unlock&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NOTE: Unlocking the bootloader will fully wipe your device. You need to confirm the unlocking procedure on the device screen. As long as you don’t lock your bootloader again, you only need to do this once.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kernel-installation&quot;&gt;Kernel installation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download the following files:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Android factory image&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TWRP images&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SuperSU ZIP&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Timur’s kernel ZIP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The factory image, TWRP recovery tool and Timur’s kernel will be dependent on the platform you have. The 2013 Nexus with WiFi will use the Flo variants of the files and the LTE version will use the Debian variants of the files. The following will be written specifically for the flo installation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unzip Timur’s kernel. Inside the ZIP are two folders of interest - “timur-kernel-n7-2013-v4.0-final.zip” and “timur-pem-update-v4-b107-2017-01-06.zip”. Unzip the kernel directory to access the USB host and services ZIPs. Both of those and the pem-update will be uploaded to the Nexus 7 in their ZIP format. These files will be installed onto the Nexus first before the SuperSU zip is installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning to Timur’s instructions:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Here I describe how you can upgrade your tablet to Android 6.0.1 MOB30X, install Timur’s Kernel v4.0 as well as root, without losing any apps or settings - and do so in under 20 minutes. To do this, your tablet bootloader needs to be unlocked once. If you already have a rooted Android 6.0.1 MOB30X with TWRP installed on your tablet, the kernel installation can be done in just a few minutes. In this case, reboot into TWRP and continue with step 4.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unzip the target Android 6 MOB30X factory image on your PC. In order to prevent the factory image installation from wiping the data partition of your tablet (if you want to keep your installed apps, personal settings and custom data), you need to edit your flash-all script (.sh or .bat, depending on what OS you are using on your PC). To keep your apps and data, remove the “-w” parameter from the last line. However, if want to delete everything on the tablet (wipe) and fully start from scratch, do not modify the flash-all script (keep the “-w” parameter in). Before you continue, this is your last chance to create a full device backup of your tablet. For instance, you can create a full device backup in TWRP recovery.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To install the factory image, connect the tablet to a PC via USB and run the (modified) flash-all script. The installation process will take a couple of minutes. This is IMPORTANT: You need to watch the tablet screen closely, because you need to prevent the tablet from booting into Android automatically at the end of the installation process. As soon as you see the tablet screen turn off, you need to quickly press power + vol-down and keep both buttons pressed for about 15-20 seconds. This will abort the boot process and instead, the tablet will return to the bootloader menu. You need to keep pressing the two buttons until you actually see the bootloader menu. This is when you can release the buttons. The point of all this is, to install TWRP and SuperSU BEFORE the newly installed Android system boots up for the first time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With the tablet in bootloader (you may need to disconnect/reconnect the PC-USB connection), you can now install TWRP recovery. You always need to do this, because flash-all will overwrite a previous instance of TWRP. To continue, enter in a command line window on your PC: “fastboot flash recovery twrp-3.0.2-0-flo.img” (if you have the LTE model, use the img-file of the deb variant). When done (only a second later), you should be able to launch the newly installed TWRP from bootloader menu. Use the volume keys to select “recovery” and then hit the power button to launch TWRP.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With TWRP recovery running, the tablet should now appear as a USB drive on your PC. This lets you copy the three zip archives required for the next step over: timur-services, timur-usbhost and SuperSU. Make sure these three files are available on the tablet’s internal sdcard. Then install the three zip files (timur-services + timur-usbhost before SuperSU!), using the TWRP on-screen UI. Note that whenever you update the kernel (usbhost), you will also need to re-install SuperSU afterwards. - OK, done. You can now restart system and boot into Android OS.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RRP:&lt;br /&gt;
The installation of the ZIPs was a bit unfamiliar to me when I started, so I’ll explain it in a bit more detail. In your terminal, change directories until you’re where your ZIP files are located. These ZIP files are outlined in the first two paragraphs of this section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To transfer the files, run the following command for each ZIP:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;adb push {insert-filename-here}.zip /sdcard/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, all of the files should be located on the tablet in the /sdcard/ directory. On the tablet, select the Install Package button and navigate to the directory. Starting with the two ZIPs from Timur’s kernel, select the file and install one at a time. These ZIPs failed the checksum of the installation when I tried, so unchecking that option before installing seems to work. After Timur’s ZIPs, repeat with SuperSU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, in order to allow the Nexus to boot automatically when powered (say the battery dies after sitting in an idle vehicle for a few months), run the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;fastboot oem off-mode-charge 0&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be done at anytime as long as the Nexus is in the fastboot menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;post-installation&quot;&gt;Post installation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the core OS is in place, a few small features can be implemented for seamless use of the device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timur’s instructions:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On first boot after installation: Do not immediately open PowerEventMgr. Instead, let the system rest in Launcher for a minute. You should see a SuperSU permission dialog show up for PowerEventMgr (PEM). Grant root access to PowerEventMgr. You can now open PowerEventMgr and, for instance, enable FI-mode and fast charging.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;VCam2 app will be installed (or updated) when you launch PowerEventMgr and click the “Launch VCam [Exec]” button. If you intend to use VCam2, you should click this button once, every time you have installed or upgraded the kernel (usbhost installer) via recovery system. Launching VCam2 for the first time will bring up a SuperSU permission dialog. It is necessary to grant VCam2 root permissions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is also possible to install VCam2 manually, by opening VCam2.apk from the /sdcard/ folder (say, using a file manager app). Once VCam2 has been installed (or updated), the file /sdcard/VCam2.apk can be deleted.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is suggested you disable SuperSU toast messages for PowerEventMgr and VCam2. To do so, open SuperSU app, select PowerEventMgr and change the Notifications setting from “Global defaults” to “Disabled”. Hit the check mark to store the modified settings. Now do the same for vcam2. And hit the check mark again to store the modified settings.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You need to disable Android OTA updates. If you allow an Android OTA to update your system, the kernel, the custom recovery and SuperSU will be removed. Do this: Long press the notification (i-icon) and block, then disable it in app settings. More:&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/timurskernel/comments/4appwx/anyone_know_how_to_remove_the_android_update_is&quot;&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/timurskernel/comments/4appwx/anyone_know_how_to_remove_the_android_update_is&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In order to use PowerEventMgr (PEM) Wakeup-screen, the Android lock-screen must be disabled (see: Security).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You probably want to enable: Settings / Developer options / Stay awake (Screen will never sleep while charging).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can view the kernel identification string under: Settings / About. It should now say “USBhost…“.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can view the version info and build number at the bottom of the PEM activity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If your system works well, re-boot into TWRP recovery mode and create a new full backup to a USB flash drive (connected via OTG cable).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Keep all of your installer files, including the correct variants of TWRP and SuperSU, in a save place.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RRP:
Now that everything is set, go ahead and install your desired Android apps and customize your system as desired. My preferred applications are outlined in the “Software Modules” section before the build guide begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hardware-installation&quot;&gt;Hardware installation&lt;/h3&gt;</content><author><name>Robert R Puccinelli</name><email>robert@robertpuccinelli.com</email></author><category term="build" /><category term="build" /><category term="jeep" /><category term="electronics" /><summary type="html">A DIY alternative to modern commercial infotainment systems in a 2001 Jeep Wrangler (TJ).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Modern Antibiotic Resistance Reporting System</title><link href="https://robertpuccinelli.com/public%20health/2017/07/05/antibiotic-resistance-reporting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Modern Antibiotic Resistance Reporting System" /><published>2017-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://robertpuccinelli.com/public%20health/2017/07/05/antibiotic-resistance-reporting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://robertpuccinelli.com/public%20health/2017/07/05/antibiotic-resistance-reporting.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;foreword&quot;&gt;Foreword:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project was conceived at the end of 2016 as I was considering solutions for meeting the various antibiotic challenges that were accepting applications at the time. Unfortunately, I was underprepared and didn’t submit an application while I could. Since then, the idea has continued to incubate in my mind for several months before being transcribed into a steno pad, followed by an electronic notebook, now followed by my website. I believe this modern approach would revolutionize how we characterize antibiotic resistances and ultimately other medical complications. As a result, the trajectory of global antibiotic resistance would be stalled or even reverted by more efficient and informed treatments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If I believe this is a great idea - why post it openly on this website?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree that it probably is quite naive for me to do this, but I currently don’t have the resources that I need to execute this idea in a timely manner and I believe this idea should be realized. I wasn’t able to join the well funded challenges several months ago, so I have started my own. Can I produce this system before another organization? It is true that I would really like to be the one who sees this idea come to fruition, but I believe that the benefit that the world would receive from this system would out do any benefit that I would receive. Why should I hold back tangible technological advancements for my own personal gain?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clock has long been ticking and it is only a matter of time before either I or some unknown character produces this system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s get going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;objective&quot;&gt;Objective:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Develop an affordable, distributed antibiotic resistance reporting system that collects and displays information in near-realtime to both characterize resistances in patient samples within a clinic and monitor the spread of resistances over space and time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;product-specifications&quot;&gt;Product Specifications:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Requirement:&lt;/strong&gt; identify antibiotic resistances in patient samples quickly and accurately.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Requirement:&lt;/strong&gt; minimize the cost barrier as much as possible so that nearly any clinic in the world can afford this system and contribute to the global data repository.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feature:&lt;/strong&gt; report probabilities of being infected by different organisms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feature:&lt;/strong&gt; produce an interactive spatial-temporal map characterizing the prevalence and spread of different resistances in near-realtime.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, in order for this technology to be adopted, it must satisfy the needs of clinics extremely well - it must be affordable and able to operate as a standalone unit in remote locations while also providing quality information. Its core purpose is to report antibiotic resistances within patient samples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the clinic permits the machine to communicate with an offsite server, additional benefits would be made possible due to access to greater computational power. Assay reports would be forwarded to a server that processes the data through a machine learned algorithm to identify the likelihood of being infected with a given organism. This would be reported back to the clinic. Also, the server will insert the report into a global database consisting of time, location and resistances reported, which would be available as an interactive map online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;proposed-assay&quot;&gt;Proposed Assay:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sample is microfluidically transferred to a cartridge containing concentration gradients of multiple antibiotics.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Raman spectroscopy (or other cell growth evaluation method) collects molecular profiles (or other metric) of the sample at t=0.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cartridge/sample is incubated for 2 hours or so.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Growth metric is collected once more at t=end.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Client machine reports probabilities of resistances to user or a minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data is stored as a blockchain report on the client machine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If client machine is connected to a server, blockchain report is forwarded for species identification processing and inclusion to the interactive spatial-temporal map. If client machine is not connected to a server, blockchain report will continue to be appended and will be forwarded upon reconnection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;if-you-would-like-to-contribute-to-offer-advice-for-or-support-this-project-feel-free-to-contact-me-i-am-not-interested-in-spinning-this-into-a-startup-that-becomes-indebted-to-venture-capitalists-or-other-funding-sources&quot;&gt;If you would like to contribute to, offer advice for, or support this project, feel free to contact me. I am not interested in spinning this into a startup that becomes indebted to venture capitalists or other funding sources.&lt;/h3&gt;</content><author><name>Robert R Puccinelli</name><email>robert@robertpuccinelli.com</email></author><category term="public health" /><category term="antibiotic resistance project" /><category term="commentary" /><summary type="html">An overview of the specifications for a yet-to-be-created antibiotic resistance reporting system.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Build Your Own: Microarray Printer</title><link href="https://robertpuccinelli.com/build/2017/07/04/build-microarrayer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Build Your Own: Microarray Printer" /><published>2017-07-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://robertpuccinelli.com/build/2017/07/04/build-microarrayer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://robertpuccinelli.com/build/2017/07/04/build-microarrayer.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;align-center width-75&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_CapturedDNA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Small protein spots capture various fluorescent DNA sequences from a solubilized microarray.

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice--info&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PURPOSE:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Provide a DIY alternative to expensive commercial microarray solutions. Benefits of this system include high-throughput spotting and microarray customizability. It was initially built and documented by Joe DeRisi and team back in the late 90’s. One of these machines was assembled for the Fordyce lab at Stanford in 2016 and is documented here for others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As per Wikipedia:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A microarray is a multiplex lab-on-a-chip. It is a 2D array on a solid substrate (usually a glass slide or silicon thin-film cell) that assays large amounts of biological material using high-throughput screening miniaturized, multiplexed and parallel processing and detection methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, if you want to do a high-throughput study with proteins, DNA, or other molecules, there’s a possibility that a microarray could fit your needs. In my opinion, the most significant advantage of using microarrays is being able to correlate a spatial signal to a known agent. It should also be noted that microarrays have been slowly phased out over the years due to advances in other technologies, but they still hold niche roles in science and medicine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The microarray golden era was somewhat before my time, so I don’t know many details of how it rose and fell. From what I understand though, microarrays and microarrayers were solely a commercial product that were sold at somewhat exorbitant prices with limited customizability in the 90’s. Joe DeRisi worked with a few others in Pat Brown’s lab at Stanford to make an open-source system that could be replicated by other labs at a fraction of the price. They created a manual for assembly and developed software to operate the machine, which several groups used for their own systems. Given that many microarrays were nucleic acid based (ie the ViroChip), the use of these systems declined as alternative technologies such as sequencing and digital PCR became more prominent. For some time, I was fortunate enough to be able to operate Joe’s microarrayer at UCSF before it was disassembled and had the opportunity to construct one of the machines for the Fordyce lab at Stanford. Since most of the assembly material has been written previously, I’ll either be posting the original material, filling in some missing information or providing files that I created to supplement the existing material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The microarrayer presented here has quite a few advantages and disadvantages that need to be considered before assembling. The greatest disadvantage by far is the sheer size of the machine. It sits on a large vibration-dampening table that’s about 6 feet wide and 4 feet long. In addition to that, it will need to be operated in a humidified environment in order to produce respectable arrays. (This latter constraint is eased by using droplet dispensers.) Traditionally, this environment was either a dedicated microarrayer room or a series of tarps hung from the ceiling. To control humidity, 3 or 4 large humidifiers were run throughout the print to maintain ~65% relative humidity. On the other hand, benefits include the ability to handle any full-skirt 384 plates, ability to handle any pins for spotting arrays, ability to print 30,000 spots on 261 slides in 20 hours, and flexibility in programming the arrays. In terms of throughput and customizability, it’s hard to beat. In terms of required spacing between spots, the limiting factor will be how large the pins spot the glass slide. Once the axes have been warmed up, the linear encoders prove to be very accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;short-demo-video&quot;&gt;Short Demo Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following video shows the print head printing spots onto 2x3 inch glass slides. In this example, the arrayer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cleans the pins and returns to the source plate for the next set of samples.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Draws samples from (4) adjacent wells on a 384 well plate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prints (4) replicates of the samples on two regions of the glass slide.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advances to the next slide until all slides are arrayed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Returns to the cleaning station.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;210&quot; height=&quot;150&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TOcTtWNRr2k&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;microarrayer-assembly&quot;&gt;Microarrayer Assembly&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature__wrapper&quot;&gt;

  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;View 1.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;View 2.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer2.jpg&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Before slide platter and pin arms.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer3.jpg&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_ArrayerPins.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Silicon microarray pins formerly employed by the DeRisi lab.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_ArrayerPins.jpg&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_ServoControllers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Axes are powered and controlled by servo controllers.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_ServoControllers.jpg&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For assembling the machine, there are no resources better than the &lt;a href=&quot;#MGuide&quot;&gt;M-Guide&lt;/a&gt;, which was produced and revised by DeRisi’s team. Nearly every detail is covered - such as how to wire all of the axes or build the dust cover to protect the slides during a print. In the early 2000s, the whole build (including parts and tools) cost about $43,000, which was a fraction of the price of other options at the time. Since then, the price for the materials or commercial options have fallen. Maybe it was just luck, but I was able to find a nearly complete DeRisi style microarrayer selling for $4,000 at the time of writing this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t go into detail about how to assemble it because it has already been written so well. However, I do want to note that some custom parts that I designed for the calibration arm or printing arm and printing block can be found in the &lt;a href=&quot;#CAD&quot;&gt;Parts List and Files&lt;/a&gt; section below. Not listed there is information on how to make the slide platter. It may be best to contact Joe for that information, but it includes some specialized boring techniques that most machine shops don’t have from what I understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;microarrayer-software&quot;&gt;Microarrayer Software&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature__wrapper&quot;&gt;

  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Win98.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;A bit outdated.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Win98.jpg&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_DeRisiArrayMaker.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Software pulled from cached site.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_DeRisiArrayMaker.png&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_ArrayMaker.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;ArrayMaker screenshot.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_ArrayMaker.png&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_DMC18x2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Galil programming reference.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_DMC18x2.jpg&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Gemini.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Gemini servo reference.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Gemini.jpg&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless you happen to have a PC happily running Windows 98, it might be best to not dwell here. Although the DeRisi group did produce software to control the microarrayer, it has aged and it might be best to rewrite a program for yourself. The ArrayMaker software and operating manual was pulled from an archived version of Joe’s website and can be found in the &lt;a href=&quot;#software&quot;&gt;Parts List and Files&lt;/a&gt; section below. This software isn’t the latest version (2.78), but it could still prove to be a useful resource regardless. Possibly, the most important thing to note here is that most of the instructions programmed will either be for the Galil DMC-18x2 motion control card or the Gemini servo controllers. Images of their reference guide are posted above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;parts-list-and-files&quot;&gt;Parts List and Files&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;guides&quot;&gt;Guides&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/pdfs/DeRisi_MGuide.pdf&quot;&gt;DeRisi M-Guide&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a name=&quot;MGuide&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/pdfs/DeRisi_ArrayerPrinting.pdf&quot;&gt;DeRisi Printing Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/pdfs/Puccinelli_ArrayerPrinting.pdf&quot;&gt;Puccinelli Printing Guide&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;software&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;software&quot;&gt;Software&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned previously, the control software produced by the DeRisi group is out-of-date and is listed here for reference only or if you happen to have a functioning Windows 98 computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/software/DeRisi_ArrayMaker_v260.zip&quot;&gt;ArrayMaker v2.60&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a name=&quot;CAD&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;arrayer-cad-files&quot;&gt;Arrayer CAD Files&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provided here are a series of custom parts that I designed to set up the arrayer at Stanford. These are virtually identical to the parts that were used by the DeRisi lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/CAD/170704_ArrayerParts.zip&quot;&gt;Download AutoCAD and SolidWorks drawings here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;feature__wrapper&quot;&gt;

  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer_BlockBody_Solid.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Pin block body - solid.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer_BlockBody_Solid.png&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer_BlockBody_Xray.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Pin block body - X-ray.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer_BlockBody_Xray.png&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer_BlockHead.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Head for block body.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer_BlockHead.png&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer_PrintingArm.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Printing arm.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer_PrintingArm.png&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer_CalibratorArm.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Calibrator arm.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer_CalibratorArm.png&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer_CalibratorMount.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Calibrator mount.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer_CalibratorMount.png&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  
    &lt;div class=&quot;feature__item&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item&quot;&gt;
        
          &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-teaser&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer_DelrinBlock.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
            
          &lt;/div&gt;
        

        &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-body&quot;&gt;
          

          
            &lt;div class=&quot;archive__item-excerpt&quot;&gt;
              &lt;p&gt;Delrin block.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;/div&gt;
          

          
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170704_Arrayer_DelrinBlock.png&quot; class=&quot;btn &quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;arrayer-cad-notes&quot;&gt;Arrayer CAD Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things to note that might not be obvious from the design files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pin Block Body&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will need some 1.5mm dowels press fit in the top and lower inner lip to support the colimiter plates that align the silicon pins.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will need (4) 2.5mm diameter x 5mm length magnets press fit into the bottom to mount the magnetic plate that holds the lower colimiter plate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will need top (4) holes tapped for M2 to mount the head.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will need back (2) holes tapped for M6 to mount to printing arm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pin Block Head&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will need a soft and compressible foam cushion that fills the void between the pins and the head. This cushion protects the pins from vibrations and acts as a spring to ensure contact with the glass slide while printing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colimiter Plates&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will be fairly expensive to machine due to the size of the features and the tight tolerances. These were initially designed to work with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.parallel-synthesis.com/smt-info.htm&quot;&gt;Parallel Synthesis Technologies&lt;/a&gt; SMT pins, but may be compatible with others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Printing Arm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attaches the pin block body to the z-axis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calibrator Arm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attaches the calibrating pin and mechanical switch to the z-axis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will need to be tapped for M2 to attach the calibrator mount.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calibrator Mount&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attaches the mechanical switch to the calibrator arm.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will need to be tapped for M2 to attach the mechanical switch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delrin Block&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Couples the slide platter to the x-axis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will need to be tapped for M6 for the holes that don’t attach to the x-axis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Robert R Puccinelli</name><email>robert@robertpuccinelli.com</email></author><category term="build" /><category term="build" /><category term="electronics" /><summary type="html">A DIY alternative to commercial microarray solutions to reduce equipment costs and enhance throughput. Based on the DeRisi style microarrayer.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Build Your Own: Gel Illumination and Imaging Chamber</title><link href="https://robertpuccinelli.com/build/2017/07/02/build-gel-chamber.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Build Your Own: Gel Illumination and Imaging Chamber" /><published>2017-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://robertpuccinelli.com/build/2017/07/02/build-gel-chamber</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://robertpuccinelli.com/build/2017/07/02/build-gel-chamber.html">&lt;p class=&quot;notice--info&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PURPOSE:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Provide a DIY alternative to expensive commercial gel imaging solutions. Benefits include exposing operators to fewer hazardous materials, reducing equipment cost and possibly improving image quality. It was initially designed for the Fordyce lab at Stanford in Dec 2014 and was further modified in July 2017 to improve the design of the door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional DNA gel staining and imaging often includes staining the DNA with ethidium bromide followed by imaging the gel with a UV light source. This is worrisome for a few people who frequently handle these materials due to the known mutagenic activity of the materials and these people are often looking to minimize their exposure when possible. As a result, some labs have transitioned over to using less hazardous stains, such as the Sybr series, and light sources, such as blue LED transilluminators. Here, I provide schematics and a list of parts for constructing a gel imaging station. Feel free to modify the design files to fit your own needs and preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gel-chamber&quot;&gt;Gel Chamber&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half &quot;&gt;
  
    
      &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170702_GelBox_Xray.png&quot; title=&quot;Gel box X-ray view.&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170702_GelBox_Xray.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;
    
  
    
      &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170702_GelChamber.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Gel box prototype.&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170702_GelChamber.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;
    
  
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Gel box design.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The imaging chamber itself is assembled with 0.5” acrylic panels held together internally by brackets and is designed to mount a low end Canon DSLR above a Clare Chemical DR89 blue LED transilluminator. The Canon DSLR was chosen due to its ability to be externally viewed and triggered by either either a workbench computer or the operator’s laptop. The transilluminator does not necessarily need to be from Clare Chemical, but the system was initially chosen due to its large 25 x 22 cm viewing surface and decent quality. The port on the right panel was designed to be compatible with the power cord for this transilluminator. You can modify this as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The acrylic box has W x L x H dimensions of 14” x 14” x 15.5” without the camera attached. The width and length was chosen to be compatible with the previously identified transilluminator and the height was chosen to provide a large enough field-of-view for the camera. AutoCAD drawings can be downloaded in the &lt;a href=&quot;#PartsList&quot;&gt;Parts List and Files&lt;/a&gt; section below. STL files may be uploaded at a later date or upon request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice--primary&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; The design was updated on 20170702 to improve the door design. Previously, the door had trouble closing due to contact with the workbench and contact with the rightmost threshold. To account for these issues, the top and bottom of the door was trimmed by 2mm and the right edge was trimmed by 3mm. The right edge also received a 45° chamfer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acrylic panels were machined by Kyle Brutschy at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfmachineworks.com/&quot;&gt;SF Machine Works&lt;/a&gt; with the following specifications:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Panel&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Face&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Quantity&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Diameter&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Depth&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Tapped&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Back&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Inner&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1360”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.25”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8-32&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1066”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.25”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6-32&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Left&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Inner&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1360”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.25”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8-32&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1066”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.25”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6-32&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Top&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Inner&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1360”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.25”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8-32&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Through&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.2010”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thru&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1/4-20&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Right&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Inner&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1360”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.25”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8-32&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1066”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.25”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6-32&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Through&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.3900”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thru&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Front&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Inner&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1360”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.25”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8-32&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1066”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.25”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6-32&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Outer&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1360”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.25”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8-32&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Door&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Outer&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1360”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.25”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8-32&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Through&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.1770”&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thru&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gel-imaging&quot;&gt;Gel Imaging&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To image the gel, a high pass filter is necessary to block out the blue light. Clare Chemical provides orange filtered glasses and a panel to lay over your gel to view results. This is good for quick viewing, but not necessarily sufficient for imaging. The camera was ultimately outfitted with 58mm Tiffen filters that attach to the lens like most polarized filters so that the gel can be placed onto the transilluminator and imaged quickly with good quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To image, Canon has free remote imaging software known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usa.canon.com/internet/portal/us/home/support/self-help-center/eos-utility&quot;&gt;EOS Utility&lt;/a&gt;, which makes viewing, capturing and saving gel images incredibly easy. After the focus has been set and once the software is installed on an imaging workstation or laptop, color correction, exposure and aperture settings can be programmatically adjusted in realtime. It’s as easy as clicking the virtual shutter release button to transfer the image to the computer. Its not necessary to use a Canon here, but it was chosen because its software is known to be easy to use for external triggering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits for using a DSLR include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Instant transfer to operator’s laptop.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The 12+ megapixel camera often has a higher resolution than most commercial gel imaging stations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The zoom lens can be adjusted for close up images of gel bands or left zoomed out to capture large field-of-view images with an exposure of approximately one second.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half &quot;&gt;
  
    
      &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170702_SampleGel1.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Zoomed gel view. (Compressed image)&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170702_SampleGel1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;
    
  
    
      &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170702_SampleGel2.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Large field-of-view. (Compressed Image)&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/170702_SampleGel2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;
    
  
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The gel box allows for small or large field of views
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;parts-list-and-files&quot;&gt;Parts List and Files&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the machined acrylic panels and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.clarechemical.com/transilluminator.htm&quot;&gt;Clare Chemical DR89 Transilluminator&lt;/a&gt; , all of the parts were either acquired from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mcmaster.com/&quot;&gt;McMaster-Carr&lt;/a&gt; or Amazon. For acrylic panels, check with your local machinist or plastics store such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tapplastics.com/about/locations&quot;&gt;TAP Plastics&lt;/a&gt;. For blue LED transilluminators, feel free to use any that can fit within a 13” x 13” space and meet your budget needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chamber-cad-files&quot;&gt;Chamber CAD Files&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/CAD/170702_GelChamber-Packaged.zip&quot;&gt;Download AutoCAD drawings here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mcmaster-carr-parts&quot;&gt;McMaster-Carr Parts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Part Number&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Quantity&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Camera Brace&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15275A66&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bracket Galvanized Steel, 1-7/8” &amp;amp; 3-1/2” Length of Sides&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mcmaster.com/#15275a66/=18ezdou&quot;&gt;View on McMaster&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Corner Bracket&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1088A31&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;nside Corner-Reinforcing Bracket, 2” Length of Sides&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mcmaster.com/#1088a31/=18eze30&quot;&gt;View on McMaster&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Edge Braces&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1556A41&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bracket Galvanized Steel, 1” Length of Sides&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mcmaster.com/#1556a41/=18ezee2&quot;&gt;View on McMaster&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Adjustable Friction Hinge&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1791A44&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Adjustable-Friction Hinge, 200 lb. Capacity, 1-11/16” High Leaf, 1-7/16” Width, Black&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mcmaster.com/#1791a44/=18ezemo&quot;&gt;View on McMaster&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Cabinet Door Knob&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11645A11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ABS Plastic Pull Knob Black Finish, 1-5/16” Knob Diameter, 1” Projection&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mcmaster.com/#11645a11/=18ezex7&quot;&gt;View on McMaster&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t remember if the door knob fit well on this because it originally came with a 1” wood screw, but it could be usable. It might be worth looking for an alternative knob or screw. Also, things not listed here include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A few short 1/4-20 screws to mount the camera to the bracket and the bracket to the top panel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;8-32 with 0.25” or shorter depth for corner brackets and door hinges.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6-32 with 0.25” or shorter depth for edge braces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Black electrical tape to block light from the gap between the panels. The panels we received were slightly smaller than 0.5” (around 0.47”).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;amazon-parts&quot;&gt;Amazon Parts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Part&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Approx $&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Camera&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$403&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Canon EOS Rebel T3i Digital SLR Camera with EF-S 18-55mm f/3.5-5.6 IS Lens (discontinued by manufacturer)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2tVST2y&quot;&gt;View on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Filter 1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$18&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tiffen 58mm 12 Filter (Yellow)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2tYXbpE&quot;&gt;View on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Filter 2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$31&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tiffen 58mm 21 Filter (Orange)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2tVStJw&quot;&gt;View on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;AC Adapter (replaces camera battery)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$19&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Kapaxen ACK-E8 AC Power Adapter Supply Kit For Canon EOS Rebel T5i / T4i / T3i / T2i / 700D / …&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2sCgx0m&quot;&gt;View on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Alternative Transilluminator (Not Tested)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$869&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Huanyu Instrument DUT-48 Blue Light Transilluminator wavelength 470nm&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2tZ4Wfn&quot;&gt;View on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Filter 1 and Filter 2 will stack onto each other and mount to the camera lens. The order for stacking isn’t important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Amazon links above were provided by the Amazon Services LLC Associates Program, which is an affiliate advertising program that gives this website an opportunity to earn some money while connecting you to products that have been or can be used for completing the project you are viewing. Any money earned will be used for covering costs associated with registering this website or the costs of the projects posted here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert R Puccinelli</name><email>robert@robertpuccinelli.com</email></author><category term="build" /><category term="build" /><category term="imaging" /><summary type="html">A DIY alternative to commercial gel imaging solutions to reduce exposure to hazardous materials and reduce upfront equipment costs.</summary></entry></feed>